A Guide to the Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs Records, 1942-2003
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs Records, 1942-2003
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-020
2.9 cu. ft. 5 boxes
The Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs Records contains program papers, correspondence, and publications relating to the VFGC from 1942-2003.
Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Federation of Garden Club Records were donated to Special Collections in 2006.
Historical Note
The Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs is a non-profit educational organization based out of Richmond, VA and is the state affiliate of the National Garden Club. They provide information on a variety of topics including flowers, gardening, and environmental responsibility, and also sponsor scholarships for students interested in horticulture and grants for community and youth projects.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs Records contains program papers, correspondence, and publications relating to the VFGC from 1942-2003. The bulk of the collection contains programs that members could borrow to watch or present at regional club meetings. Some of the papers are written presentations, while others contain slides and slide descriptions. A few programs also have cassette tapes.
The collection also houses some correspondence relating to previous program chairs, mostly giving feedback on the various program papers they had used. The collection is completed with yearbooks from the Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs, handbooks from the local garden club chapter, and a few educational books and pamphlets.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series--Series I: Program Papers, Series II: Correspondence, and Series III: Pamphlets and Publications. The first series contains the program papers, in alphabetical order. The second series contains correspondence to program chairs, arranged by individual, in chronological order. The third series contains various publications, separated to local handbooks, VFGC Yearbooks, and other publications, with each group arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following VHS tapes have been removed from the collection and cataloged for the Special Collections Media Collection:
Gardening from the Ground Up - Herbs
Gardening from the Ground Up - Bulbs
Gardening from the Ground Up - Annuals, Bi-Annuals, Perennials
Gardening from the Ground Up - Landscaping
Man of the Trees
Integrated Pest Management
New Dimensions in Floral Design
Voices of Vision: The Future of Virginia's Environment
Your Water Your Life
Perennial Gardening
The Art of Landscaping Design
The Art of Landscaping Shopping and Planting
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Contents List
- Series I: Program Papers 1959-2001.
  - A Day at Nature Camp, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - A Layman's Observation of Birds, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - A Williamsburg Christmas, 1985. (Box-folder 1-3, Box 5)
  - American and Canadian Beauty Spots, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - American Holly, 1978. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Annual Flowers, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Attractive Driveway Entrances, 1959. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Basic Culture of Spring Flowering Bulbs, 2001. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Birds, 1957. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Birds in the Backyard, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Bluebirds, Land and Sky, 1995. (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Boxwood in the Landscape, 1977. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Butterflies and Butterfly Gardening, 1992. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Chelsea Flower Show - London, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Christmas Fantasy, 1977. (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Christmas in Williamsburg, n.d. (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Daffodils Proclaim Spring, n.d. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Daylilies, n.d. (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Design of the Home Grounds, 1975. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Exhibition 50, n.d. (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Flower Arrangements of Colonial Williamsburg, 1986. (Box-folder 1-21, Box 5)
  - Flower Arrangements of Williamsburg, n.d. (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Flower Festival at the Washington Cathedral, n.d. (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Fragrance Gardens, 1979. (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Gardening in Small Containers, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Gladiolus, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Green Survival Landscaping, 1975. (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Growing and Exhibiting Daffodils, 1999. (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Herbs, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
  - "Heritage Reflections," A Standard Flower Show, 1976. (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Horticulture and Landscape Design, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
  - "How to Do It" Plans for Attracting Birds, 1974. (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Ikebana, 1998. (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Joyful Jubilee, 1964. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Landscaping, n.d. (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Landscaping Slopes, 1973. (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Microwave Drying of Flowers, 1980. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Native Flowers and Animals of Australia,Hawaii, New Zealand, and Tahiti, n.d. (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Nature Camp, n.d. (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Our Heritage, n.d. (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Plant Material that Will Attract Butterflies, 1991. (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Program Papers for Juniors, n.d. (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Propagation of Cacti, 2000. (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Pruning Shrubs and Trees, n.d. (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Ruby Throated Hummingbirds, 1995. (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Shrubs in the Landscape, n.d. (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Stories Found in Plants, 1997. (Box-folder 2-23)
  - The Ruby Throated Hummingbird, 1987. (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Trees for Virginia Gardens, n.d. (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Vegetable Garden Planting and Culture, n.d. (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Virginia Ferns and Fern Allies, 1975. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Voices of Vision: The Future of Virginia's Environment, 1987. (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Washington Cathedral Altar Arrangments, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Water - We Can't Live Without It, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 3-7, Box 5)
  - Who Says Vegetable Gardening Isn't Fun?, n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Wildlife Neighbors of the Williamsburg Area, 1983. (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Williamsburg Gardens, 1985. (Box-folder 3-10, Box 5)
  - Williamsburg Gardens, n.d. (Box-folder 3-11)
- Series II: Correspondence 1997-2002.
  - Mary Westfall Correspondence, 1997-2001. (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Zelia Lawrence Correspondence, 1998-2002. (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Helen Smith Correspondence, 2001-2002. (Box-folder 3-14)
- Series III: Pamphlets and Publications, 1942-2003.
  - Arboretum Garden Club Handbooks, 1958-1980. (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Arboretum Garden Club Handbooks, 1980-1992. (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs Yearbook, 2003. (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Other Pamphlets and Publications, 1942-1977. (Box-folder 4-3)
    Bibliography
    Homes and Flowers: Refreshing Arrangements, 1942
    "Restoring Accessories," 1963
    "Design for Flowers," 1968
    "How to Combine the New and the Old," 1968
    Handbook for Flower Shows, 1977
    Golden Memories, n.d.
    "Table Settings," n.d.